Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be
learning about the world of buffers.
So in this particular video, this is an
introductory video to understand what the
concept of a buffer is and how exactly you
can pick and choose how to make a buffer.
So with this one, the idea of what a
buffer solution is, is that a mean teens,
the pH by resisting changes in the pH.
Okay.
So meaning that if you add a very
tiny amount of acid or base, it's
going to neutralize that acid or base.
So what the whole idea here is, I have,
I've drawn here is I have a buffer
solution on the left hand side here.
And what we have inside
is a little pH probe.
So when you dip a probe in the
solution, it lets you know the pH.
Now, if you add an acid to it, or a base.
One thing is you're gonna notice is that
the concentration is did not change much.
It originally was at a seven,
and currently at the moment
you see that it's at a 6.9.
After you made it more acidic and
it's at a 7.1 when you made it more
basic on the other side, right?
So there was not much of a change.
So when it comes to add a
buffer, it resists change.
The pH is relatively maintained.
It's an equilibrium process.
So meaning that you tried to make the
reaction go forward, but it resisted it.
It went.
So whenever we are looking at this
compared to let's say a solution of
water, for example, well, if I have
just water with my probe, I'll measure
the pH and it's a seven, right?
That's the normal pH for neutral water.
Now if I add an acid to it.
You're going to see that the pH is
going to change very, very quickly.
So see this at a four, I add the exact
same amount of acid to the buffered
one and to the, to the, to water
and it changed dramatically, right?
It changed drastically.
If I added a base, the same amount
that I added above to water, it
changed all the way to an 11.
You see that it went a huge difference.
So pH changes an insane amount
when you just add it to water
or any regular solution.
When an acid or base is
added, a buffer resists.
So how does that exactly work?
Let's take a look.
The whole idea of when it comes
to buffers is they re they
essentially resist the pH change.
When we add acids or bases now with
something like this is extremely important
Especially when it comes to the human
body The body has natural buffer systems
built into it to help essentially preserve
Cellular and body function and the main
reason it does that is because essentially
all the food and drinks and beverages
you eat and drink Are all very acidic
and very basic and will affect the pH
balance of your system One big example
of that is let's say if you eat like a
lot of acidic fatty food maybe and you
get a really upset stomach, well that's
because you had a little bit too much
acid in your system, but over time you're
going to feel better and your body will
get back to its state of equilibrium.
So the body essentially absorbs protons
or H3O plus and hydroxides to maintain.
This is very important
for how your cells behave.
And how your blood, blood
functions within the body.
Um, whenever it comes to something like
trying to maintain the pH, what it's
essentially doing is by neutralizing
with the different components of
it, it's going to help it stabilize.
So, let's try to take a little
bit, a little bit farther to look
exactly how, how does this work?
You didn't exactly explain it.
Let's go even farther.
Have a weak acid or base and
it's with its conjugate partner.
It will resist pH changes.
So, whenever you have a, whenever
you have an acid or a base added.
It's going to actually neutralize
that acid or base and help maintain
pH by resisting the change.
Now one thing that makes that
so important is that the human
body absorbs acids and bases.
And the way it absorbs us from all the
food and drinks that essentially we ingest
on a regular everyday basis, and from
your natural cellular processes of just
keeping you running on a, on a day to
day day on just the regular day to day.
So if you eat and drink, you know,
whatever it is, let's say if you have
like fast food or soda or something,
or even just any like sugary, any
fruit drinks, a lot of them are very
acidic, which if you have them, it's
going to offset the pH of your body.
But the thing is your body has built
in buffer systems to make sure that
doesn't happen because if you drank
one acidic thing, it'd be like poison.
You'd fall over dead,
but that doesn't happen.
Why?
Um, so essentially whenever you
have a buffer, it's very important
to cell and blood function.
It means teens, the pH.
So one big example is that your
blood with all of your blood cells
in it is a giant buffer system.
And one example of that is
let's say if I have a carbonic
acid, which is in your blood.
And we were to combine that
with its conjugate base, it
would help maintain the system.
So its conjugate base in this case, if
you remember, differs from one single
proton will help maintain that pH.
And the other beauty of something like
carbonic acid is that it can even go
one more step to help hold, whether it's
more acidic or more basic, depending on
how you're breathing, how your body's
functioning, it will maintain it.
Let's take a look at how we make it and
try to make this make a little more sense.
So now the whole idea of what are
the different components of a buffer.
So as I said before, it has to be
the conjugate acid base pair, meaning
that generally we take a weak acid
and we combine it with the salt.
of its conjugate base, and they
have to be in equal concentrations.
So let's take a look at what that
exactly represents through an example.
So let's say if I want to create
a buffer of acetic acid, we would
need a salt of its conjugate base.
Now, the salt is added to provide a
higher concentration of the conjugate
base because if you add just acetic acid
into solution, it barely dissociates.
So it's not going to have
a lot of it in there.
So let's try to take a look
and try to understand how do we
pick which salt that we have.
So if I have acetic acid, well, if I
lose, let's say a proton and dissociate
in water, so if we have an H plus.
What's going to be left?
We're going to have C2H3O2
as its conjugate base.
So if we have the conjugate base, and
then we have an acid, well, what could I
use as a salt for this particular thing?
Well, some examples of that would be
if essentially any alkali metal bonded
to that, uh, to that acetate ion.
So let's say if I took sodium.
acetate and I bonded those two together.
So if we just take our acetate and
cut and cut and paste that we can bond
those two different pieces together.
This would be one example.
Another example of a salt
could be like maybe potassium
acetate could be another one.
Essentially, anything that has that
salt component to help create that ion.
Because if I take, let's say
sodium acetate, and I were to
throw that into solution, well,
what exactly would you make?
You'd make sodium, right?
And the acetate ion.
So you would need to add both
of them into a solution to make.
It consists of both.
So let's say if I wanted to pick how
you would make the best buffer solution
possible, if they were mixed in equal
portions, how would you do that?
Well, the first little check box is
that it needs to be a weak acid, right?
So either a weak acid or a weak base.
So let's just go with a
weak acid to make it easier.
So what we are going to do is we're
going to add an X to anything that's
considered to be a strong acid.
So that means no.
So let's look at anything
that can't be used.
So if I go through my candidates
here, we want to kind of look at our
different acids that are available.
So if we highlight our acids,
we have a bunch of them.
Which one of these are considered
to be strong, weak, what do we have?
Well, the first thing that you
have is we have HBr, right?
HBr is one of your strong acids.
It's bromic acid.
So even though it's going to be
with its salt, it won't, it will
be too many ions in solution.
It won't be enough of the
original one in there.
So that's a no.
Now if I have the next one,
HCN and HI, are they a pair?
Well, remember they have to
differ by a single proton.
And if I compare these two molecules.
They differ by a carbon and a nitrogen.
That's a big no.
That's not going to be okay.
Um, if we go to the next one, well, if I
compare H2CO3 and sodium bicarbonate, do
these, do these differ by a single proton?
And you'll see that it is.
It's different by just one
proton and we have that sodium.
So that's a salt.
So that tells you, hey, you
have, you found your salt.
That's here.
That's what the sodium part is.
And what is the essential, uh, part of H
two CO three is that it needs to be able
to dissociate to make HCO three minus.
Okay.
Now even looking at the other ones, right?
Hi makes I minus h plus that
doesn't, that didn't match either.
Now, so that could be a
really good candidate.
So let's put a little green check mark.
Now, is it the best?
I don't know yet.
So if we look at the last one,
right, that this other one,
this H I that's a strong acid.
So that's a no.
And the last one is sodium
hydroxide and water.
Well, water is considered
to be the acid here.
Would this be considered to
dissociate the right way?
So if I take H2O, it would
make H plus and OH minus.
Well, OH minus and sodium are together.
But hydroxide, what is that?
That's a strong base.
So that's gonna be a no as well.
So we found our choice with carbonic
acid because that is with its salt.
So this is how you pick
out the correct buffer.
It needs to be a weak acid.
with its conjugate base salt.
And you can do the same with
a weak base and its conjugate
acid as well, but generally it's
more common to use a weak acid.
Let's take a look at another example.
Which of the following would make
the best buffer solution if mixed
in roughly equal proportions?
So here we don't have pairs, we
have all these individual pieces.
So the first thing you kind of want
to do is let's try to see if we can
eliminate any, um, common pairs so
that, or especially anything that's
considered a strong asset or a base.
So if we kind of look over here, well
what exactly can we use, what can we use?
So we have the first one,
you can see that we have HCL.
HCL is a strong acid.
So what we can kind of quickly
do is we can say that's a no,
that's not gonna quite work.
Um, from there we have a couple
weak, we have, we wanna look for
any other acids that can be used.
So we have a phosphoric acid as a choice.
Um, and then there's no other
acid that's available to us.
So if we were to look at this, well,
H 3 0 3, P oh four, if essentially,
if that were to dissociate,
you would need H two P oh four.
Minus.
Um, and that needs to be
connected to some kind of salt.
So can we see anything
that would quite match?
And if you look below it, well,
essentially, KH2PO4 almost
matches perfectly, right?
They are almost identically the same.
In this case, you have
the salt stabilizing it.
So these two would be a great
pair to have for your answer.
Now what about the last one?
Lithium, we have lithium,
uh, with L I B R O.
And then nabra is the
other one, N A B R O.
They're both salts, but neither
one of them is an acid, so
that's gonna be a no go.
And then NACL is just a salt, so
that's not going to be okay either.
So we have our pair.
And that's the whole idea of this, is
can we try to pick which one we have.
So when it comes to buffers,
they resist your pH changes,
and that's the whole idea.
Now, the last concept about buffers is
all about this idea that we can actually
quantify how the buffer actually works.
So before we talked about how
we can make a buffer and, and
somewhat how, what it is doing.
So just to emphasize that most important
fact is that a buffer, it is absorbing
either the acidic quality, which is
the H plus or H3O plus from solution.
Or the oh minus, and the whole idea
is that it tries to maintain the
pH at where it's designed to be.
Now with a buffer, this does it
within a certain capacity, so this is
referred to as the buffer capacity.
It can hold the pH within one of
wherever the buffer is designed to work.
So every single chemical series
of buffers works at a different pH
value, and this is something we can
calculate, which I'll show you how
to do just for a more basic, simple
buffer for how this whole idea works.
So this is a kind of illustrated,
at least the way that I can think
how to make this make sense is that
a buffer, the whole idea first is
that you have the acid, you have and
it, the salt of its conjugate base.
And with, when both molarities of each one
equal each other, you have your buffer.
So this is the pH where it works.
Now the concept here is, let's
say if I want to kind of play with
the actual chemical reaction here.
So if I have an acid and I add it
to water and I have the conjugate
base, how does this concept work?
Well, it's all about equilibrium and how
it can shift from one way to another.
The goal is to keep the
reaction in the middle.
So if all of a sudden I decide to increase
the amount of base in the solution, well,
what is the buffer going to exactly do?
Well, when we increase that, it's
going to try to absorb it, right?
It's going to try to keep
it into the center here.
Now, so when you add more base to the
solution, it has to respond to that.
Is it going to let it become basic?
Well, no, or the entire
system is going to fall apart.
What's going to happen then is being that
this whole reaction here has this double
arrow that we've talked about before.
Well, the reaction can either happen.
in the forward direction
or in the reverse.
So if all of a sudden I decide to
increase the basic side, which is the
A minus, well, what is going to happen
to, to essentially to change this?
Well, the system is going to respond
and instead it's going to actually
try to shift the reaction backwards.
It's like oh There's too much
product laying around So in order to
change the scales of this reaction
and how everything is balanced,
it's going to shift it back back.
So when all of a sudden you increase
a lot of base here, you're going
to now see that the reaction is
going to shift back to the center.
It's going to try to hold it there.
And that's what a buffer does.
It neutralizes all these different
components as being added to you.
Like your blood or your circulatory
system, when you introduce something
that's basic to your body or acidic, your
body is trying to maintain its levels
so that it can operate appropriately.
It has to be kept in the middle.
So if I do the opposite, where all of
a sudden I'm like, well, I want to now,
uh, have all these acids in my body.
So let's say you drink a bunch
of soda or you, uh, have a bunch
of energy drinks or coffee.
Well, what's your body going to do?
Is it just going to let it become acidic
and allow it to kind of poison itself?
And yeah.
No, it's going to, it's
going to fight back.
So when you have something that's very
acidic being added to your body, well,
instead of it shifting, uh, in the
reverse direction, like we did before,
it's now going to cause it to shift
forward in order to neutralize itself.
So being that when we increase a
ton of acid, it's now going to shift
forward to respond to that change.
It's all about, is there a response?
And that's how the idea
of buffers, they respond.
And resist change of pH.
Let's try to look at this one basic
calculation to finish this video.
So when it comes to actually trying to
analyze where does your buffer work, this
is all about understanding what is the Ka
value and actually eventually deriving an
equation that can be used to be able to
determine how well does your buffer work.
So if I had the following, it says
that the Ka for acetic acid Uh, is 1.
8 times 10 to the negative 5.
What is the pH of the buffer, uh, that
is prepared with 1 molar acetic acid?
And then one molar of acetate
ion, which is the conjugate base.
So if I were to do that, how
would the entire thing work?
How would we set this up?
Right?
We never talked about
something like this before.
Well, the one thing we can do is we can
set up a Ka equation in that we have a Ka.
So what we will first do is,
well, if you remember, is that Ka.
so is equal to the products over
the reactants of your formula.
So if we have our Ka, what we
will do is put our products, which
in this case is H3O, uh, or H3O
plus, and we have our acetic acid.
And remember, all these are
referred to in brackets as well.
So we have our products
all over the reactants.
And then we'll take that expression.
Now, from here, what we can essentially
do is we can kind of rearrange it to
actually solve for what is the pH.
Well, so exactly how do you do that?
Well, if you kind of remember
from your equations, is that pH
is equal to the negative log of
OH, of negative log of H3O plus.
So what we have to actually do is
rearrange this formula to get H3O plus.
By itself.
So can we do that?
Well, if we kind of do some mathematics,
just to sort of cancel things out.
So for example, if I were to look
at this and I were to, let's say,
multiply both sides, by the acid
and base, so to cancel things out.
So let's kind of move things around.
So what I'm doing here is I essentially
am multiplying by the opposites, so
that way everything cancels our units.
So as we can see, the
conjugate base cancels.
acid cancels.
So we're multiplying and
dividing by the different sides.
So when we do that, we now have
on the right hand side, the Ka
multiplied by the conjugate, by
the acid and the conjugate base.
So both those concentrations.
So we're sort of rearranging
this equation, in order
to get H3O plus by itself.
Now the whole reason we're doing this is
so that way we can actually find the pH.
Now the last step is all about well
in order to find pH you have to
take the negative log of everything.
So if we kind of do do that take
the negative log of our H3O plus
concentration we would have pH is equal
to the negative log of Ka times the
negative log Of our concentrations.
So now, why is this something
that's so important?
Well, this is essentially how we define
the Henderson Hasselbalch equation,
which is quite the complicated name.
So now, what this whole idea is, by
deriving this, this, this Ka with
a negative log is actually known
as something known as the pKa.
So what we do here is we take
that negative log of the Ka.
negative log of our,
of our acids and bases.
And it actually, we can plug all
of our different components in
that we started with the problem.
So if I take my pH is equal to
negative log of our K a value,
which from earlier was 1.
8 times 10 to the negative five.
And then essentially we multiply
that by the negative log of our
concentrations, which were one over one.
So it was one mole.
Divided by one mole, and the whole
thing is that number over there
is going to end up cancelling out.
And once we put all this
into our calculator by
taking the negative log of 1.
8 times 10 to the negative 5th, times
it by the negative log of 1 divided
by 1, what we are going to get is
the pH of where this buffer works.
Which, after we place that into your
calculator, you're going to get a pH of 4.
74.
is where this buffer works.
So if you had acetic acid as
a buffer, it would be able to
maintain a pH right around 4.
74, which the kind of let you
know, it's like to go back up
to the example I had earlier.
So earlier I talked about, well,
if the concentrations were equal to
each other, which is what we had,
well then essentially the buffer
would be able to hold right around 4.
74.
So it could either increase the
pH by one or decrease it by one.
So within our buffer capacity, it
could hold the pH from anywhere from 3.
74 all the way to 5.
74 in order to maintain
it within a pH of 2.
Now this is very critically important
for biological systems which have enzymes
and proteins um, that essentially are
very sensitive to the pH without them
being in their very specific ranges.
They will denature, they will
cease to function correctly, they
won't be able to react properly.
So this is the general idea
of things that you'll see in
physiology and in future courses.
This is the idea with buffers, uh,
just to be able to wrap this up.
So let's take a look
at our final thoughts.
Most important concept here
is that buffers resist pH.
You can do a lot of calculations with
these, but this is something that's
beyond the scope of introductory
chemistry, but it will be featured
in future videos later on.
Um, in terms of other courses that are on
this page, but when it comes here, buffer
just maintains the pH or resists that
change, which is the ultimate thing here.
You need the weak acid with,
with its conjugate base,
and that's how you pick it.
So you have to know what a buffer
is because it's something that's
commonly used in all biology classes,
especially in physiology, microbiology.
And in chem chemistry, one B and
in a lot of different chemical
engineering applications as well.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope this helped.
And if it, if you need help, please
reach out to me and let me know if
there's anything that I can do to help.
Um, if, if you are someone that needs
help with your course, feel free to
either message me or comment below.
Let me know what you thought.
Um, and if it's your first time
here, hit that like and subscribe
button and support the video.
I really appreciate that.
And thank you so much for listening.
I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll see you later.
Bye now.